<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the entrance of the Swedish armie into the territories of the King of Denmark; and the taking of some notable towns therein; the said Swedes having denounciated open war against the King of Denmarke, for his unjust taxations and dealings with them. Extracted out of a letter from a merchant-adventurer in the city of Hamburgh. Wherein we may take notice of Gods providence in frustrating the King of Denmarks designe to assist our King against the Parliament. Published by order.</title>
            <author>Merchant-adventurer in the city of Hamburgh.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E79_31</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873105</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125559</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92365)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125559)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 14:E79[31])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the entrance of the Swedish armie into the territories of the King of Denmark; and the taking of some notable towns therein; the said Swedes having denounciated open war against the King of Denmarke, for his unjust taxations and dealings with them. Extracted out of a letter from a merchant-adventurer in the city of Hamburgh. Wherein we may take notice of Gods providence in frustrating the King of Denmarks designe to assist our King against the Parliament. Published by order.</title>
                  <author>Merchant-adventurer in the city of Hamburgh.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Rich. Cotes, and Jo. Raworth,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Decemb. 30. 1644. [i.e. 1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sweden --  History --  Dano-Swedish Wars, 1643-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125559:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION Of the Entrance of the Swediſh Armie Into the Territories of the King of <hi>DENMARK<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the taking of ſome notable Towns therein; the ſaid Swedes having denounciated open War againſt the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> for his unjuſt Taxati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Dealings with them.</p>
            <p>Extracted out of a Letter from a Merchant-Adventurer in the City of <hi>Hamburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein we may take notice of Gods providence in fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Deſigne to aſſiſt our King againſt the PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Rich. Cotes,</hi> and <hi>Jo. Raworth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Decemb.</hi> 30. 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:125559:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125559:2"/>
            <head>A Relation of the entrance of the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Army into the Territories of the King of <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope the Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners from the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee at <hi>London,</hi> will effect much good from the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Swedes</hi> have denunciated open Warre againſt the King, for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125559:3"/>
his unjuſt Taxations and dealings with them: Generall <hi>Dorſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> with the greateſt part of the <hi>Swedes</hi> Army, are come downe into the <hi>Holſtein</hi> Land; the came unexpectedly, having Marched with ſuch celerity, as never was known; they have Marched with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe ſixteene dayes, above a hundred <hi>Dutch</hi> miles: Their counſels and determinations have beene ſo privately ordered, that none knew of their intentions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they came into the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Territories: They have beſieged and taken <hi>Crimp;</hi> which place hath beene of great conſequence to the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> but was not provided to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125559:3"/>
withſtand the Power of the <hi>Swedes.</hi> It is conceived they will re-Fortifie the ſaid Towne, and leave a Garriſon there. It is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe reported, That the Gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall was before <hi>Kiel</hi> on Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day laſt, and hath taken in a Houſe (which belongs to the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi>) neare adjacent to the Towne, and at length hath alſo taken <hi>Kiel.</hi> It is conceived that hee will finde great Treaſure in the Towne; reports are various, ſome ſay ten hundred thouſand Rixdollors, but I thinke, if he finde halfe the ſumme, hee will be contented, and Advance into the bowels of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markes</hi> Countrey. They are all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125559:4"/>
in ſecurity, and have not made any preparation to withſtand the Army of the <hi>Swedes;</hi> ſo it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that they will ruinate his Countrey before the King will be able to collect an Army which can oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe reported, That the <hi>Swedes</hi> have entred <hi>Denmarke</hi> on the other ſide, they having had an Army of ſeven or eight thouſand men in readineſſe upon Borders of his Countrey, ſo that while he raiſeth Forces to oppoſe the one Army, the other will over-runne and ruine great part of his Countrey. The <hi>Swedes</hi> Generall hath ſent a Meſſenger to this Towne of <hi>Hamborough,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125559:4"/>
the Senate, that he intends no hurt to them or their Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, and that if any prejudice ſhould enſue unto them by the inſolent and diſorderly carriage of his Souldiers, hee would bring them to demerited puniſhment. The Duke of <hi>Holſtein</hi> hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe to be Newtrall, ſo the <hi>Swedes</hi> feare not any oppoſition.</p>
            <p>It is almoſt incredible, to think of the great quantitie of Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, Armes, Gold and Silver, with other rich Booties that they have already taken.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:125559:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>REader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>take notice of this, That one hundred <hi>Dutch</hi> Miles, is foure hundred <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles; for an Army to March in the ſpace of ſixteene dayes, was ſo great a thing that the like was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of before</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:125559:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
